<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="pretty-atom-feed.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Blog Title</title>
  <subtitle>This is a longer description about your blog.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://example.com/feed/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://example.com/" />
  <updated>2026-01-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://example.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Your Name</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Shrinking the Tactile Experience: A Dive into Miniature Haptics</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/blog/firstpost/" />
    <updated>2026-01-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/blog/firstpost/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Imagine you&#39;re 8 years old again, sitting in the back of a car, wiggling your fingers against the window to make a little hand-person perform sick parkour moves along the power lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out that childhood habit is actually a recognized interaction technique called &lt;strong&gt;Finger Walking in Place (FWIP)&lt;/strong&gt;. While digging through &lt;strong&gt;CHI Conference&lt;/strong&gt; archives for a Human-Computer Interaction class last semester, I found a project from National Taiwan University that takes this imaginary play and turns it into a high-tech reality: &lt;strong&gt;Miniature Haptics&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/joO-F2Gzlm0?si=6mNQtRoMlLU7tOul&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The core idea? Instead of building massive, expensive treadmills to simulate walking in VR, why not just &amp;quot;shrink&amp;quot; the person and map their body onto their hand?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a huge fan of Ready Player One, I&#39;ve always viewed total digital immersion as the &amp;quot;north star&amp;quot; for tech. We’ve gotten great at showing digital worlds, but we’re still missing the &lt;em&gt;feeling&lt;/em&gt;. Most home systems are limited to basic controller vibrations with the same &amp;quot;buzz&amp;quot; representing a sword clashing or a car engine idling - completely different tactile experiences! &lt;strong&gt;Miniature Haptics&lt;/strong&gt; solves this by leveraging the &amp;quot;Embodiment Illusion&amp;quot; to make your hand feel what your character feels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-concept-finger-walking-as-embodiment&quot;&gt;The Concept: Finger Walking as Embodiment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TThe researchers found that people are surprisingly good at mapping their mental skeletal model to their fingers. In their mapping study, there was a massive overlap in how users envisioned their &amp;quot;hand-person&amp;quot;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Index and Middle Fingers:&lt;/strong&gt; Become your legs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Back of the Hand:&lt;/strong&gt; Becomes your torso.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Wrist:&lt;/strong&gt; Becomes your head.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;concept-callout&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Why this matters:&lt;/strong&gt; By shrinking the scale, we can experience things that would be dangerous or impossible at human-scale, like the physical impact of a football hitting your head or walking across rapidly shifting terrain without 4D theaters or motion simulation theme park attractions.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;kicking-miniature-footballs&quot;&gt;Kicking Miniature Footballs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To test this, the team built a haptic display using &lt;strong&gt;6 micro linear actuators&lt;/strong&gt; with tiny footballs attached. When your virtual avatar &amp;quot;kicks&amp;quot; a ball, the actuator physically strikes your finger at the exact moment of impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In their study, this &amp;quot;Miniature Haptics&amp;quot; approach was &lt;strong&gt;2.3 times more preferred&lt;/strong&gt; than a standard vibrating game controller. Users reported that the physical sensation made the experience feel significantly more enjoyable, realistic, and intuitive compared to monotonic vibrations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-i-m-obsessed&quot;&gt;Why I&#39;m Obsessed&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As someone who spends a lot of time thinking about game design and animation, this opens up a huge door. Imagine playing a game where you don&#39;t just see your OC move but also you feel the weight of their steps through your fingertips as you navigate a forest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As VR gaming and 3D Vtubers are on the rise, I see this as a great way to physically bridge the gap between ourselves and the digital worlds we build.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;concept-callout source-box&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Source:&lt;/strong&gt; Wang et al. (2020). Miniature Haptics: Experiencing Haptic Feedback through Hand-based and Embodied Avatars. CHI &#39;20.
&lt;p&gt;You can find the full paper and technical specifications on the ACM Digital Library here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3313831.3376292&quot;&gt;Miniature Haptics: Experiencing Haptic Feedback through Hand-based and Embodied Avatars&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>